he went out to see what was cast ashore during a recent storm. And on a patch of grass right next to the water's edge, he found a wetsuit. It was grey and black, and he thought it looked cheap. Out of each leg of the wetsuit there were sticking two white bones. It was clearly the remains of a human being. And usually, in Norway, dead people are identified quickly. So the police started searching through missing reports from the local area,
salió para ver los efectos en la orilla de una reciente tormenta. En una zona de hierba justo hasta donde llega el agua, encontró un traje de buzo. Era gris y negro y parecía barato. Por el final de cada pierna del traje salían un par de huesos blancos. Sin duda eran los restos de un humano. En Noruega, los cadáveres suelen identificarse rápido. y la policía empezó a investigar en informes de desapariciones de la zona,
national missing reports, and looked for accidents with a possible connection. They found nothing. So they ran a DNA profile, and they started searching internationally through Interpol. Nothing. This was a person that nobody seemed to be missing. It was an invisible life heading for a nameless grave.
en informes nacionales. buscaron en accidentes que pudieran tener relación. No encontraron nada. Realizaron una prueba de ADN y, a través de la Interpol, buscaron en el extranjero. Nada. Era persona que parecía que nadie echara de menos. Una vida invisible hacia una tumba sin nombre.
But then, after a month, the police in Norway got a message from the police in the Netherlands. A couple of months earlier, they had found a body, in an identical wetsuit, and they had no idea who this person was. But the police in the Netherlands managed to trace the wetsuit by an RFID chip that was sewn in the suit. So they were then able to tell that both wetsuits were bought by the same customer at the same time, October 7, 2014, in the French city of Calais by the English Channel. But this was all they were able to figure out. The customer paid cash. There was no surveillance footage from the shop. So it became a cold case. We heard this story, and it triggered me and my colleague, photographer Tomm Christiansen, and we of course had the obvious question: who were these people? At the time, I'd barely heard about Calais, but it took about two or three seconds to figure out Calais is basically known for two things. It's the spot in continental Europe closest to Britain, and a lot of migrants and refugees are staying in this camp and are trying desperately to cross over to Britain. And right there was a plausible theory about the identity of the two people, and the police made this theory as well. Because if you or I or anybody else with a firm connection to Europe goes missing off the coast of France, people would just know. Your friends or family would report you missing,
Entonces, un mes después, la policía noruega recibió un mensaje de la policía holandesa. Un par de meses antes, habían encontrado un cadáver en un traje de neopreno idéntico y no sabían quién era la persona. La policía holandesa pudo restrear el traje a través de un chip de radiofrecuencia cosido al traje. Así pudieron afirmar que ambos trajes los compró la misma persona, a la misma hora. El 7 de octubre de 2014, en la ciudad francesa de Calais en el canal de la Mancha. Y eso fue todo lo que pudieron saber. Ese cliente pagó en efectivo. No había cámaras de seguridad en la tienda. Fue caso cerrado. Oímos la historia, y Tomm Christiansen, fotógrafo, quedamos impactados. Nos hicimos la inevitable pregunta: ¿quiénes eran esas personas? Aunque a penas sabía nada de Calais, me llevó dos o tres segundos averiguar que Calais era conocida por dos cosas. Es la zona de Europa continental más cercana a Gran Bretaña. Muchos inmigrantes y refugiados viven en un campamento e intentan cruzar hasta Gran Bretaña a toda costa. Ahí había una posible teoría sobre la identidad de los cadáveres y la policía intuyó lo mismo también. Si Uds. yo u otra persona conectados a Europa desapareciera en la costa de Francia, la gente lo sabría. Amigos o familia denunciarían su desaparición,
the police would come search for you, the media would know, and there would be pictures of you on lampposts. It's difficult to disappear without a trace. But if you just fled the war in Syria,
la policía le buscaría, la prensa lo anunciaría y pondrían fotos en farolas. Es difícil desaparecer sin dejar rastro. Aunque si huyes de la guerra de Siria
and your family, if you have any family left,
y tu familia, si es que aún tienes,
don't necessarily know where you are, and you're staying here illegally amongst thousands of others who come and go every day. Well, if you disappear one day, nobody will notice. The police won't come search for you because nobody knows you're gone. And this is what happened to Shadi Omar Kataf and Mouaz Al Balkhi from Syria. Me and Tomm went to Calais for the first time in April this year, and after three months of investigation, we were able to tell the story about how these two young men fled the war in Syria,
no sabe con certeza dónde estás y estás aquí de forma ilegal entre miles de personas que van y vienen a diario. Claro que si desapareces un día nadie se dará cuenta. La policía no te buscará porque nadie nota que has desaparecido. Eso es lo que le ocurrió a Shadi Omar Kataf y a Mouaz Al Balkhi, ambos sirios. Tomm y yo fuimos a Calais por primera vez en abril y después de tres meses investigando podíamos contar la historia de dos jóvenes sirios que escaparon de la guerra de Siria
ended up stuck in Calais, bought wetsuits and drowned in what seems to have been an attempt to swim across the English Channel in order to reach England. It is a story about the fact that everybody has a name, everybody has a story, everybody is someone. But it is also a story about what it's like to be a refugee in Europe today. So this is where we started our search. This is in Calais. Right now, between 3,500 and 5,000 people are living here under horrible conditions. It has been dubbed the worst refugee camp in Europe. Limited access to food, limited access to water, limited access to health care. Disease and infections are widespread. And they're all stuck here because they're trying to get to England in order to claim asylum. And they do that by hiding in the back of trucks headed for the ferry, or the Eurotunnel, or they sneak inside the tunnel terminal at night to try to hide on the trains. Most want to go to Britain because they know the language, and so they figure it would be easier to restart their lives from there.
y, al no poder irse de Calais, compraron trajes de buzo y se sumergieron en el intento de cruzar a nado el canal de la Mancha hasta Inglaterra. Es la historia de cómo todos tenemos un nombre todo el mundo tiene una historia y todo el mundo es alguien. Pero también es la historia de qué significa ser un refugiado en Europa. Aquí es donde empezó nuestra búsqueda. Esto es Calais. Actualmente viven aquí entre 3000 y 5000 personas en unas condiciones horribles. Lo llaman el peor campamento de refugiados de Europa. Acceso limitado a comida, acceso limitado a agua, acceso limitado a sanidad. Enfermedades e infecciones por todos lados. Están atrapados ahí porque quieren llegar hasta Inglaterra y poder solicitar asilo. Y lo intentan escondiéndose en camiones que viajan en ferry, o por el Eurotúnel. O se cuelan por la noche en la terminal del túnel para esconderse en los trenes. La mayoría quiere ir a Inglaterra porque conocen el idioma y creen que les resultará más fácil retomar sus vidas ahí.
They want to work, they want to study, they want to be able to continue their lives. A lot of these people are highly educated and skilled workers. If you go to Calais and talk to refugees, you'll meet lawyers, politicians, engineers, graphic designers, farmers, soldiers. You've got the whole spectrum. But who all of these people are usually gets lost in the way we talk about refugees and migrants, because we usually do that in statistics. So you have 60 million refugees globally. About half a million have made the crossing over the Mediterranean into Europe so far this year, and roughly 4,000 are staying in Calais. But these are numbers, and the numbers don't say anything about who these people are, where they came from, or why they're here. And first, I want to tell you about one of them. This is 22-year-old Mouaz Al Balkhi from Syria. We first heard about him after being in Calais the first time looking for answers to the theory of the two dead bodies. And after a while, we heard this story
Quieren trabajar, quieren estudiar, quieren poder seguir viviendo sus vidas. Muchos tienen estudios superiores y están cualificados. Si vas a Calais y hablas con ellos, conocerás a abogados, políticos, ingenieros, diseñadores gráficos, granjeros, soldados... Encuentras todos los oficios. Pero quiénes son estas personas deja de saberse cuando hablamos de refugiados y de emigrantes porque solemos usar estadísticas. Si hay 60 millones de refugiados en total, sobre medio millón han cruzado este año el Mediterráneo para llegar hasta Europa y unos 4000 viven en Calais. Pero eso son solo cifras, y las cifras no dicen nada sobre quiénes son esas personas, de dónde vienen o por qué están aquí. Quiero hablarles de uno de ellos. Este es Mouaz Al Balkhi, 22 años, de Siria. Supimos de él la primera vez que estuvimos en Calais, buscando respuestas a la hipótesis para los dos cadáveres. Tras un tiempo, oímos la historia
about a Syrian man who was living in Bradford in England, and had been desperately searching for his nephew Mouaz for months. And it turned out the last time anybody had heard anything from Mouaz was October 7, 2014. That was the same date the wetsuits were bought. So we flew over there and we met the uncle and we did DNA samples of him, and later on got additional DNA samples from Mouaz's closest relative who now lives in Jordan. The analysis concluded the body who was found in a wetsuit on a beach in the Netherlands was actually Mouaz Al Balkhi. And while we were doing all this investigation, we got to know Mouaz's story. He was born in the Syrian capital of Damascus in 1991. He was raised in a middle class family, and his father in the middle there is a chemical engineer who spent 11 years in prison for belonging to the political opposition in Syria. While his father was in prison, Mouaz took responsibility and he cared for his three sisters. They said he was that kind of guy. Mouaz studied to become an electrical engineer at the University of Damascus. So a couple of years into the Syrian war, the family fled Damascus and went to the neighboring country, Jordan. Their father had problems finding work in Jordan, and Mouaz could not continue his studies, so he figured, "OK, the best thing I can do to help my family would be to go somewhere where I can finish my studies and find work." So he goes to Turkey. In Turkey, he's not accepted at a university, and once he had left Jordan as a refugee, he was not allowed to reenter. So then he decides to head for the UK, where his uncle lives. He makes it into Algeria, walks into Libya, pays a people smuggler to help him with the crossing into Italy by boat, and from there on he heads to Dunkirk, the city right next to Calais by the English Channel. We know he made at least 12 failed attempts to cross the English Channel by hiding in a truck. But at some point, he must have given up all hope. The last night we know he was alive, he spent at a cheap hotel close to the train station in Dunkirk. We found his name in the records, and he seems to have stayed there alone. The day after, he went into Calais, entered a sports shop a couple of minutes before 8 o'clock in the evening, along with Shadi Kataf. They both bought wetsuits, and the woman in the shop was the last person we know of to have seen them alive. We have tried to figure out where Shadi met Mouaz, but we weren't able to do that. But they do have a similar story. We first heard about Shadi after a cousin of his, living in Germany, had read an Arabic translation of the story made of Mouaz on Facebook. So we got in touch with him. Shadi, a couple of years older than Mouaz, was also raised in Damascus. He was a working kind of guy. He ran a tire repair shop and later worked in a printing company. He lived with his extended family, but their house got bombed early in the war. So the family fled to an area of Damascus known as Camp Yarmouk. Yarmouk is being described as the worst place to live on planet Earth. They've been bombed by the military, they've been besieged, they've been stormed by ISIS and they've been cut off from supplies for years. There was a UN official who visited last year, and he said, "They ate all the grass so there was no grass left." Out of a population of 150,000, only 18,000 are believed to still be left in Yarmouk. Shadi and his sisters got out. The parents are still stuck inside. So Shadi and one of his sisters, they fled to Libya. This was after the fall of Gaddafi, but before Libya turned into full-blown civil war.
de un hombre sirio que vivía en Bradford, Inglaterra, y que había buscado desesperado a su sobrino Mouaz durante meses. Resultó que la última vez que alguien supo algo de Mouaz fue el 7 de octure de 2014. El mismo día en que se compraron los trajes. Viajamos hasta allí y conocimos al tío. Le tomamos muestras de ADN y también se tomaron muestras del pariente de Mouaz más cercano, que vive en Jordania. Los análisis concluyeron que el cuerpo encontrado en la playa, en Holanda, era de Mouaz al Balkhi. Mientras realizábamos toda esta investigación, pudimos conocer la historia de Mouaz. Nació en la capital siria de Damasco en 1991. Se crió en una familia de clase media. Su padre, el del centro, es ingeniero químico que pasó 11 en la cárcel por pertenecer a la oposición política. Durante la ausencia de su padre, Mouaz asumió la responsabilidad de cuidar de sus 3 hermanas. Él era así, nos dijeron. Mouaz estudió ingeniería eléctrica en la Universidad de Damasco. Tras dos años del comienzo de la guerra, la familia dejó Damasco y viajaron hasta el país vecino. En Jordania, su padre no podía encontrar trabajo y Mouaz no pudo seguir con sus estudios. Pensó: "Lo mejor que puedo hacer para ayudar a mi familia es ir a algún lugar donde pueda acabar mis estudios y encontrar un trabajo". Así que, viajó a Turquía. En Turquía, no le aceptaron en ninguna universidad y al haberse ido Jordania como refugiado no podía volver a entrar al país. Entonces, decidió irse al Reino Unido, donde vivía su tío. Consigue llegar a Argelia, camina hasta Libia, paga a un traficante de personas para poder llegar en barco a Italia y, desde allí, se dirige a Dunkerque, una ciudad que está al lado de Calais, en el canal de la Mancha. Sabemos que intentó cruzar sin éxito el canal hasta 12 veces escondiéndose en un camión. En algún momento, tuvo que perder toda fe. La última noche que estuvo vivo, se hospedó en un hotel barato cerca de la estación de tren de Dunkirk. Vimos su nombre en el registro. Parece que se hospedó allí solo. Al día siguiente, se fue a Calais, entró en una tienda de deportes un par de minutos antes de las 8 de la tarde, junto con Shadi Kataf. Ambos compraron trajes de buzo y la mujer de la tienda fue la última persona que sabemos los vio con vida. Intentamos averiguar dónde se conocieron Shadi y Mouaz, pero no pudimos lograrlo. Los dos tienen una historia similar. Nos enteramos de quién era Shadi cuando su primo, que vive en Alemania, leyó la traducción al árabe de la historia de Mouaz en Facebook. Contactamos con él. Shadi, un par de años mayor que Mouaz, también se crió en Damasco. Era un hombre trabajador. Montó una tienda de neumáticos y trabajó en una empresa de edición. Vivía con su numerosa familia, pero bombardearon su casa cuando empezó la guerra. Huyeron hasta Damasco, a una zona llamada Campo Yarmouk. Yarmouk es descrito como el peor sitio para vivir de todo el planeta. Les ha bombardeado el ejército, les han asediado, les ha atacado el ISIS y, durante años, se les ha interrumpido el suministro. Un oficial de la ONU fue el año pasado y dijo: "Se han comido todo el césped y ya no queda nada". De una población de 150 000, al parecer, solo 18 000 personas siguen viviendo en Yarmouk. Shadi y sus hermanas escaparon. Sus padres aún siguen atrapados allí. Shadi y una hermana suya huyeron a Libia. Fue después de la caída de Gaddafi, pero antes de que en Libia estallara una guerra civil.
And in this last remaining sort of stability in Libya, Shadi took up scuba diving, and he seemed to spend most of his time underwater. He fell completely in love with the ocean, so when he finally decided that he could no longer be in Libya, late August 2014, he hoped to find work as a diver when he reached Italy. Reality was not that easy. We don't know much about his travels because he had a hard time communicating with his family, but we do know that he struggled. And by the end of September, he was living on the streets somewhere in France. On October 7, he calls his cousin in Belgium, and explains his situation. He said, "I'm in Calais. I need you to come get my backpack and my laptop. I can't afford to pay the people smugglers to help me with the crossing to Britain, but I will go buy a wetsuit and I will swim." His cousin, of course, tried to warn him not to, but Shadi's battery on the phone went flat, and his phone was never switched on again. What was left of Shadi was found nearly three months later, 800 kilometers away in a wetsuit on a beach in Norway. He's still waiting for his funeral in Norway, and none of his family will be able to attend. Many may think that the story about Shadi and Mouaz is a story about death, but I don't agree. To me, this is a story about two questions that I think we all share: what is a better life, and what am I willing to do to achieve it? And to me, and probably a lot of you, a better life would mean being able to do more of what we think of as meaningful, whether that be spending more time with your family and friends, travel to an exotic place, or just getting money to buy that cool new device
Justo en ese último período de estabilidad en Libia, Shadi empezó a bucear y pasó sus días bajo el agua. Se enamoró del océano. Cuando decidió que no podía quedarse más tiempo en Libia, a finales de agosto de 2014, esperaba encontrar trabajo de buceador una vez en Italia. La realidad no fue tan fácil. No averiguamos mucho de sus viajes porque nos costó ponernos en contacto con su familia. Lo que sí sabemos es que luchó. A finales de septiembre, vivía en las calles de algún lugar de Francia. El 7 de octubre llamó a su primo de Bélgica y le contó su situación. Le dijo: "Estoy en Calais. Necesito que vengas a por mi mochila y mi computadora. No puedo pagar a los contrabandistas para poder cruzar hasta Gran Bretaña, pero voy a cruzar a nado con una traje de buzo". Su primo, claro está, intentó disuadirle, el móvil de Shadi se quedó sin batería y nunca más se volvió a encender. Lo que quedó de Shadi lo encontraron 3 meses después, a 800 kilómetros, en una playa de Noruega con un traje de buzo. Aún está esperando su funeral en Noruega y nadie de su familia podrá asistir. Muchos pensarán que la historia de Shadi y Mouaz es una historia sobre la muerte. Yo no estoy de acuerdo. Para mí, es una historia sobre dos preguntas que todos nos hacemos: ¿Qué es una vida mejor? ¿Qué estoy dispuesto a hace para tenerla? Para mí, y para la mayoría de Uds., una vida mejor sería poder tener más tiempo para lo que creemos es significativo, ya sea pasar más tiempo con la familia y los amigos, viajar a un lugar exótico, tener dinero para comprar lo último en tecnología
or a pair of new sneakers. And this is all within our reach pretty easily. But if you are fleeing a war zone, the answers to those two questions are dramatically different. A better life is a life in safety. It's a life in dignity. A better life means not having your house bombed, not fearing being kidnapped. It means being able to send your children to school, go to university, or just find work to be able to provide for yourself and the ones you love. A better life would be a future of some possibilities compared to nearly none, and that's a strong motivation. And I have no trouble imagining that after spending weeks or even months as a second-grade citizen, living on the streets or in a horrible makeshift camp with a stupid, racist name like "The Jungle," most of us would be willing to do just about anything. If I could ask Shadi and Mouaz the second they stepped into the freezing waters of the English Channel, they would probably say, "This is worth the risk," because they could no longer see any other option. And that's desperation, but that's the reality of living as a refugee in Western Europe in 2015. Thank you.
o las zapatillas de moda. Todo esto lo podemos tener fácilmente, pero si huyes de una zona de guerra, las respuestas a esas preguntas son dramáticamente distintas. Una vida mejor es una vida a salvo. Es una vida digna. Una vida mejor significa que no bombardeen tu casa, no temer que puedan capturarte. Significa poder enviar a tus hijos a la escuela, ir a la universidad o encontrar un trabajo para mantenerte a ti y a los tuyos. Una vida mejor sería un futuro con ciertas posibilidades en comparación con ninguna. Y eso es una motivación muy grande. Me es fácil imaginar que, después de pasar semanas y meses, como un ciudadano de segunda clase, viviendo en la calle o en un campamento improvisado con un nombre racista y malsonante como "La jungla", la mayoría de nosotros haría lo que fuera. Si pudiera preguntarles a Shadi o Mouaz, justo en el momento en que se hundieron en las aguas heladas del canal, seguramente me dirían: "Vale la pena arriesgarse". Ya no veían que les quedara otra opción. Eso es desesperación. Y esa es la realidad de ser un refugiado en la Europa Occidental de 2015. Gracias.
(Applause) Bruno Giussani: Thank you, Anders. This is Tomm Christiansen, who took most of the pictures you have seen and they've done reporting together. Tomm, you two have been back to Calais recently. This was the third trip. It was after the publication of the article. What has changed? What have you seen there? Tomm Christiansen: The first time we were in Calais, it was about 1,500 refugees there. They had a difficult time, but they were positive, they had hope. The last time, the camp has grown, maybe four or five thousand people. It seemed more permanent, NGOs have arrived, a small school has opened. But the thing is that the refugees have stayed for a longer time, and the French government has managed to seal off the borders better, so now The Jungle is growing, along with the despair and hopelessness among the refugees. BG: Are you planning to go back? And continue the reporting? TC: Yes. BG: Anders, I'm a former journalist, and to me, it's amazing that in the current climate of slashing budgets and publishers in crisis, Dagbladet has consented so many resources for this story, which tells a lot about newspapers taking the responsibility, but how did you sell it to your editors? Anders Fjellberg: It wasn't easy at first, because we weren't able to know what we actually could figure out. As soon as it became clear that we actually could be able to identify who the first one was, we basically got the message that we could do whatever we wanted, just travel wherever you need to go, do whatever you need to do, just get this done. BG: That's an editor taking responsibility. The story, by the way, has been translated and published across several European countries, and certainly will continue to do.
(Aplausos) Bruno Giussani: Gracias, Anders. Este es Tomm Christiansen, el fotógrafo que tomó las fotos que habéis visto trabajando juntos. Tomm, los dos habéis estado en Calais hace poco. Fue el tercer viaje. Después de la publicación del artículo. ¿Qué ha cambiado? ¿Qué habéis visto allí? Tomm Christiansen: La primera vez que fuimos a Calais, habían unos 1.500 refugiados. Lo estaban pasando mal, pero eran optimistas, tenían esperanza. La última vez, el campamento había crecido hasta unas 4.000 o 5.000 personas. Parecía estar más asentado, habían llegado ONGs, se había abierto una escuela. Lo cierto es que los refugiados se han quedado más tiempo, y el gobierno francés ha logrado acordonar las fronteras mejor, por eso La jungla esta creciendo, y también la desesperación y la desesperanza de los refugiados. BG: ¿Pensáis volver y continuar denunciando la situación? TC: Sí. BG: Anders, yo antes era periodista, y me parece increíble que en este clima de salarios recortados y editores en crisis, Dagbladet ha proporcionado muchos recursos para esta historia, lo que sugiere que los periódicos están tomando las riendas, ¿cómo la vendísteis a vuestros editores? Anders Fjellberg: Al principio fue difícil porque no podíamos saber lo que íbamos a averiguar. Cuando nos enteramos de que podíamos identificar quién era el primer cadáver, recibimos el mensaje de que podíamos hacer lo que quisiéramos, viajar adónde necesitáramos y hacer lo que tuviéramos que hacer. Acabar el trabajo. BG: Eso es un editor asumiendo la responsabilidad. Esta historia se ha traducido y publicado en varios países europeos y seguro se seguirá haciendo.
And we want to read the updates from you. Thank you Anders. Thank you Tomm. (Applause)
Y todos queremos leer vuestras novedades. Gracias, Anders. Gracias, Tomm. (Aplausos)